Guide to the Edward and Gertrude Dewey collection of Gage & Tollner records 2016.034
Brooklyn Historical Society
Edward and Gertrude Dewey collection of Gage & Tollner records
1888-2004
Brooklyn Historical Society
Pawlukiewicz, Janet Dewey
2016.034
7 Linear Feet in five manuscript boxes, two half manuscript boxes, two small flat boxes, one artifact box, and one oversize flat box.
The Edward and Gertrude Dewey collection of Gage & Tollner records consist of materials from the Gage & Tollner restaurant located at 372-374 Fulton Street in the Downtown Brooklyn neighborhood of Brooklyn, dating from 1888 to 2004. The materials were mainly collected and compiled by the Dewey family who owned the restaurant from 1919 to 1988. The records primarily document the business operation under the Dewey family's management. The Dewey family sold the restaurant to Peter Aschkenasy in 1988 and the restaurant was later closed in 2004. The highlights of the collection include photographs of the landmark building and celebrities, as well as the anniversary menus and other memorabilia that marks the significance of this 125 year-old restaurant food and dining venue in the heart of Downtown Brooklyn.
The digitized portions of this collection are available on our digital collections.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series:
Series 1: Business Records
Series 2: Photographs
Series 3: Audio recordings
Series 4: Memorabilia
Historical note
Charles Gage and Eugene Tollner opened the restaurant at 372-374 Fulton Street in 1892. The restaurant was sold to A.H. Cunningham and Alexander Ingalls in 1911 and then to the Dewey family in 1919. The restaurant's interior was landmarked in 1975 and the building was added to the National Register of Historic Places in 1982. John and Gertrude Dewey sold the restaurant in the 1980s to Peter Aschkenasy. Joseph Chirico owned the restaurant from 1995 to 2004. At that time the restaurant closed and the building was sold to the Jemal family.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Janet Dewey Pawlukiewicz, 2016.
Related Materials
The Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related materials:
75th anniversary, 1879-1954: Gage and Tollner's, Brooklyn's famous landmark restaurant. Book: Brooklyn Historical Society; Main Collection; TX945.5 .G3 1954.
Brooklyn Historical Society ephemera collection (ARC.272), Series 1: Business
Scope and Contents
The collection contains papers, photographs, audio recordings, and memorabilia of the Gage & Tollner restaurant, dating from 1888 to 2004. The collection's paper records, including ephemera, ledgers, journal books, and correspondence, document the restaurant's business and operations. The photographs in this collection depict the interior and exterior of the restaurant's landmark building, events at the restaurant, as well as its owners and employees. The collection also contains an assortment of artifacts, such as a fake mustache (part of the restaurant's branding), a light bulb, an ashtray, anniversary calendars, matches, toothpicks, pins, cardholders, and two pitchers.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
372-374 Fulton Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Advertisements; Artifacts (object genre); Ashtrays; Audiocassettes; Audiotapes; Awards; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Bottle stopper; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Commerce; Buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Business cards; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Buttons (information artifacts); Calendars; Caterers and catering |z New York (State) |z New York; Certificates; Clippings (information artifacts); Color slides; Correspondence; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Envelopes; Ephemera; Food -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fulton Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Gas-lighting |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hair (material); Historic buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Journals (accounts); Labor |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Labor disputes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ledgers (account books); Light bulbs; Licenses; Memorabilia; Menus; matches; Negatives (photographic); Photographic prints; Pitchers (vessels); Postcards; Posters; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sound recordings; Toothpicks; Brooklyn Dodgers (Baseball team); Pawlukiewicz, Janet Dewey
- Series 1: Business records, 1919-2004; 4 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes, one half manuscript box, and one oversize flat box
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains business records of the Gage & Tollner restaurant, including two folders of awards and certificates, two folders of building related files, approximately one box of anniversary and special event files, one folder of correspondence, eight folders of operations records, eight folders of ephemera, two accounting ledgers and journal books, and approximately one box of press clippings. Oversized materials are stored in Box 8. The series also contains different versions of the restaurant's menu, postcards, artworks, various promotional materials, and other items.
  Arrangement
  The series is partially arranged by subject, which reflects the records' original order. Other materials were arranged by subject and then chronologically by the processing archivist.
  - Business records (Box 1)
  - Business records (Box 2)
  - Business records (Box 3)
  - Business records (Box 4)
  - Business records (Box 5)
  - Business records (Box 8)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1888-1989; 0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and one oversize flat box
  Series contains one box of photographic prints, slides, and negatives depicting the restaurant owners, employees, various events, as well as its landmark building dating from 1888 to 1989. Oversize photographs are stored in Box 8. Photographs related to the restaurant's 75th anniversary can be found in Series 1: Business Records.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 8)
  - Photographs (Box Polaroid box 1)
  - Photographs (Box Oversize Glass Negatives)
- Series 3: Audio recordings, 1972-1985; 0.25 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box
  Series contain two quarter inch magnetic tapes and one cassette tape about the history of the restaurant dating from the 1980s.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Brooklyn Dodgers Come Home (Audio Cassette), 1985 (Box 7)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    This cassette has been digitized and is available on the Center for Brooklyn History's Internet Archive account. Listen to the audio here.
  - Gage & Tollner Restaurant "Information" (1/4 inch Open Reel), 1977 (Box 7)
    This film has been digitized and is available on the Center for Brooklyn History's Internet Archive account. Listen to the audio here.
  - The McCanns Program: All About Gage & Tollner's, Excerpt (1/4 inch Open Reel), 1972 (Box 7)
    This reel has been digitized and is available on the Center for Brooklyn History's Internet Archive account. Listen to the audio here.
  - The McCanns Program: All About Gage and Tollner's, Full Audio (1/4 inch Open Reel), 1972 (Box 7)
- Series 4: Memorabilia and Menus, circa 1930s-1984; 0.5 Linear Feet in two folders, one oversize box, two small flat boxes, and two artifact boxes
  Series consists of menus and memorabilia from Gage & Tollner restaurant, dating from circa 1930s to 1984. The menus include luncheon, dinner, dessert, and drinks. The memorabilia include two Vintage Benedict Indestructo pitchers, an original electric bulb from the restaurant, a fake mustache (part of the restaurant's branding), an ashtray, a bottle stopper, matches, pins, cardholders, toothpicks, and an oversize poster board with signatures of retired Brooklyn Dodgers baseball players (circa 1980s).
  This series has not been arranged by an archivist.
  - Memorabilia (Box 6)
  - Memorabilia (Box 8)
  - Memorabilia (Box 9)
  - Memorabilia (Box 10)
  - Memorabilia (Box 11)
  - Memorabilia (Box 12)